Fig. S3. Comparison of cell discharge performance.
Fig. S1. Cycling behavior of LIB and SEB under over-charge conditions.
Fig. S5. Elemental concentration of EEI layers.
Fig. S7. Comparison of C-rate discharge curves for the baseline LIB cell and the three SEB cells at room temperature.
Supplementary material for this article is available at http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/6/9/eaay7633/DC1
Fig. S2. Calendar life testing for LIB and SEB.
Fig. S6. Discharge curves of the fresh baseline cell versus the aged cell.
Fig. S4. Optical comparison of fresh and aged electrodes.
Funding: This work was partially supported by U.S. Department of Energy’s Office of Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy under award number DE-EE0008447. Author contributions: S.G. and C.-Y.W. developed the concept and wrote the manuscript. S.G. and R.S.L. designed and built the cells. S.G. built the test stand and carried out the performance characterization. T.L. carried out the nail penetration test. Y.L. performed the impedance analysis. Y.G. and Daiwei Wang carried out the XPS and SEM analysis. All authors contributed to development of the manuscript and to discussions as the project developed. Competing interests: The authors declare that they have no competing interests. Data and materials availability: All data needed to evaluate the conclusions in the paper are present in the paper and/or the Supplementary Materials. Additional data related to this paper may be requested from the authors.
As mentioned, such rapid heating is achieved through the insertion of a micrometer-thick nickel sheet. The impact of this additional component on cell power density can be evaluated through Eq. 1, where m is the mass of the given cell and the ratio of discharge power evaluated through HPPC is inversely proportional to the ratio of DCRs(Power Density)SEB(Power Density)baseline@RT=(DCRbaseline@RTDCRSEB@60°C)(mbaselinemSEB)(1)
Figure 3D presents the relative interfacial reactivity as derived from the charge-transfer resistance of EIS results. This further confirms that increased operational temperature effectively decreases the charge-transfer resistance of SEB cells and consequently increases the cell reactivity and power. The reactivity boost over the baseline LIB cell is 2.06 for SEB-2. Overall, both relative power and relative reactivity illustrate the ability of SEB cells to achieve high power on demand. On the other hand, the values of relative reactivity of these two cells shown in Fig. 3D indicate that the SEB cell will be 5× safer and undergo 5× less aging at room temperature, which is supported by self-discharge and capacity retention tests displayed in fig. S2. Furthermore, the comparison of relative reactivity for the two cell types at 60°C indicates that the SEB cell is more than 2× less prone to thermal runaway.
The use of the TAP additives altered the EEI compositions markedly. We performed x-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS) on the graphite and NCM electrodes after 4021 cycles and compared the EEI structure of the samples from the baseline cell after 956 cycles. At the graphite anode, the TAP-containing electrolyte-derived SEI contains high concentrations of C, O, and P elements, compared to the control sample of the baseline cell (Fig. 6 and fig. S5). In addition, a higher content of C─C species in the entire C-containing species was also found in the TAP-containing electrolyte-derived SEI, suggesting the decomposition of the TAP at the anode (fig. S5). Meanwhile, the composition of the cathode CEI was also changed. With the TAP additive, the SEI layer has more C, P, and F and less Li and O, compared to the baseline SEI (Fig. 6 and fig. S5). High contents of LiF and P-containing species (O─P═O, LixPyOFz, and LixPyFz) (9) were found in the cathode CEI layer, owing to the use of the TAP additive (Fig. 6). A detailed peak interpretation is as follows: peaks at 284.6, 286.1, 288.8, and 290.1 eV in the C 1s spectrum are attributed to C─C, C─O, O─C═O, and poly(O─C═O) (10), respectively; peaks at 684.6 eV in the F 1s spectrum are attributed to LiF; peaks at 686.9 eV in the F 1s spectrum and 136.7 eV in the P 2p spectrum are attributed to O─P═O and LixPyOFz; and peaks at 686.3 eV in the F 1s spectrum and 134.5 eV in the P 2p spectrum are attributed to LixPyFz. In comparing O 1s spectrum of the aged baseline (956 cycles) and SEB-3 electrodes (4021 cycles), the peak at 529.2 eV for SEB-3 cathode is effectively eliminated in comparison to that for the baseline cathode (Fig. 6). This indicates that less lattice oxygen of NCM622 is detected for SEB-3 cathode attendant to a relatively thicker CEI layer. This is consistent with the thicker CEI layer detected by Xia et al. (2) on the coated NMC442 surface in the presence of TAP additive. Thus, the XPS result confirms that the TAP additive leads to a thick CEI layer and, in consequence, slower crack evolution, less gas generation, and longer cycle life.
The addition of the nickel foil increases cell mass by 1.3%, while the ratio of DCRs in Eq. 1 is the relative power presented in Fig. 3C at 60°C. On the basis of these values, the power density is not reduced but rather increased by a factor of 2.02, 1.79, and 1.37 in the case of SEB-1, SEB-2, and SEB-3, respectively. Thus, in the case of SEB-3 with the highest internal resistance, the power density is still 37% higher than the baseline cell operated at room temperature.
The three SEB cells show very close rates of capacity fade within 1000 cycles (Fig. 4A). Beyond 1000 cycles, SEB-3 shows a much lower rate of capacity fade than the other two SEB cells, as expected from its lowest reactivity. In comparison with the baseline cell, the stability and long cycle life of SEB cells are clearly evident, the reasons of which can be delineated from the differences in the capacity retention trend at various stages of aging. For the baseline cell, we see a sharp decrease in C/3 capacity retention during the initial stage and a slow decrease in the secondary stage. This is primarily attributed to the loss of lithium inventory during the quick and slow growth of the SEI layer. For the SEB cells, the capacity fade is linear with cycle number, indicating that there is no quick growth in the initial stage of aging as SEI layer growth is suppressed by in situ formation of the flame-retardant protective layer. Moreover, a sharp, nonlinear capacity loss due to lithium plating can usually be observed in the baseline cell at room temperature and at low temperatures in final stages of cell aging (11). In all SEB cells operated at 60°C, this lithium plating-induced capacity loss is, however, absent, indicative of no lithium plating in SEB cells. The SEB cell free of Li plating offers a significant improvement in safety over conventional LIB cells.
The tremendous extension of cycle life of the SEB over the baseline cell may stem from the denser and more stabilized SEI layer formed on graphite particles and CEI layer on NCM622 particles in the presence of the electrolyte additives. For the baseline cell, the nickel-rich NCM particles are prone to microcracks along grain boundaries (5, 6) that provide gaps for electrolyte penetration and lead to more severe electrolyte oxidation and rock salt formation (7). Particle cracking also sets free new, fresh surface area from which oxygen can be released (8). The microcracks on NCM622 particles for the baseline cell are observed after only 50 cycles (Fig. 5D). The formation of cracks becomes much more notable throughout the micrograph domain after 956 cycles (Fig. 5F). For the SEB cells, cracks on NCM particles are not observed at 50 cycles, and a small amount of cracks are observed after 4021 cycles (Fig. 5J). The presence of microcracks not only causes a loss of contact but also accelerates NCM capacity fade. For the SEB cells, the polymer coating from TAP likely forms a robust CEI, reducing formation of microcracks (Fig. 2B). This is also evidenced by optical images (fig. S4) and no observable cell deformation or swelling after 4021 cycles even at an elevated temperature of 60°C.
Beyond safety and high power, there is an ever-increasing need for long cycle life of LIBs. Low-reactivity SEB cells built with highly stable materials offer longer calendar life (fig. S2), evident from the slow capacity fade when the battery is in idle conditions at room temperature. At elevated temperatures, cycling of SEB cells is also stable. Figure 4A compares capacity retention of the baseline cell with SEB cells during cycling at 60°C of 1C CC charge to 4.2 V CV charge till C/20 and then 1C discharge to 2.8 V. Clearly, the SEB cells outperform the baseline cell as evidenced by a 20% capacity loss at 481 cycles with visible signs of cell deformation due to gas evolution and graphite anode swelling for the baseline cell, while SEB-3 can achieve 2821 cycles before reaching 20% capacity loss. This corresponds to ca. 6× improvement in cycle life. In addition, SEB-3 achieves 4014 cycles at 75% capacity retention while still showing signs of a healthy cell capable of cycling stably (no perceptible gassing or lithium plating). The average discharge capacity of these 4014 cycles is 84.2% of an equivalent full cycle (EFC). Assuming a 153-mile driving range per EFC for an electric vehicle (e.g., 2019 BMW i3), the 4014 cycles mean >517,000 miles of lifetime. That is more than 5× the warranty for commercial electric cars (e.g., BMW i3, 70% capacity for 8 years or 100,000 miles). Improvement of cell lifetime can be further demonstrated by considering the rate of capacity fade during calendar aging at room temperature (i.e., the stable state), which is 7× lower than that at 60°C (the reactive state). The SEB cell will only be heated to the reactive state for situations requiring high power or fast charging. The greater part of its lifetime (>90%) would be spent in idle conditions (the stable state). Therefore, in the field, the SEB cycle life is expected to extend much beyond 4014 cycles before reaching 25% capacity loss.
Because of the high-voltage tolerance of SEB cells, when charged to a high voltage of 4.4 V as compared to 4.2 V, the SEB cell discharge capacity increases 12.7%, and its discharge energy increases 14.5% (fig. S1B). Thus, the high-voltage tolerance can be used to increase cell energy density.
PolyTAP and its composites are flame-retardant materials. In addition, the PolyTAP has electrically insulative properties and stability at elevated temperatures (4). All these properties make PolyTAP well suited to enhance the safety of SEB cells under abuse conditions. This is confirmed by nail penetration tests shown in Fig. 2C, where the temperature rise is only 100°C (without cell deformation, smoking, or fire) versus almost 1000°C (catching fire) in the baseline case (Fig. 2D). The superior safety performance of the SEB cell is further illustrated by the electrical performance of the cell during nail penetration. For the baseline cell, the cell voltage decreases to 0.1 V within 5 s after the nail penetration. The sharp voltage drop indicates that the shorting current is extremely high due to low internal resistance of the baseline cell. In contrast, the voltage of the SEB cell drops from 4.171 to 3.085 V within 5 s after penetration, showing a slow and controlled discharge due to the high internal resistance of the SEB cell. The substantially higher resistance in the SEB cell than the baseline is caused by the electrically nonconductive layers formed on the surface of the graphite and NCM particles, as schematically shown in Fig. 2B.
As a proof of concept, we prepare a baseline cell composed of a standard electrolyte, 1 M LiPF6 in ethylene carbonate (EC)/ethyl methyl carbonate (EMC) (3/7 wt) + 2 weight % (wt %) vinylene carbonate (VC), and a graphite anode and an NCM622 cathode. Protective layers of solid electrolyte interphase (SEI) on graphite and cathode electrolyte interphase (CEI) are formed during initial charge/discharge cycles. To yield low DCR and hence high power, these interfacial layers are usually thin, lacking sufficient density and resilience to resist decomposition under abuse conditions, to suppress continuous reaction of the solvent EC in the SEI, or to hinder continuous oxidation of EC with oxygen released from cathode materials in the CEI, thereby leading to Li consumption and loss of cell capacity. In contrast, in SEB cells, we create highly stable, flame-retardant EEIs through the addition of a small amount of TAP in the standard electrolyte. This electrolyte modification is accompanied by the simultaneous reduction of EC content, i.e., EC/EMC (1/9 wt) + 2 wt % VC, intended for further reduction in gas production via side reactions. In this work, we present results for three prototype SEB cells, identified as SEB-1, SEB-2, and SEB-3 and corresponding to 0.5, 1, and 1.5 wt % TAP, respectively. The charge-transfer resistance of the SEB cells, measured by electrochemical impedance spectroscopy (EIS), increases by 3× to 5× as compared to the baseline cell without the electrolyte additives, as shown in Fig. 2A. The high impedance comes from the polymerization of TAP molecules that form thick and dense interfacial films at the surfaces of both the anode and cathode (2). On the anode side, the film serves as an enhanced SEI layer to stabilize further growth. On the cathode side, the film hinders EC in the electrolyte from reacting with lattice oxygen on the NCM surface at high temperature or high voltage (3), as shown schematically in Fig. 2B.
With the introduction of new materials into the electrolyte, the effect on cell cost, weight, and fabrication should be evaluated. The electrolyte additive, TAP, has a comparable price and density when compared to current standard solvents; thus, no notable material cost difference is expected with the introduction of SEB electrolytes. Unlike superconcentrated electrolytes (14), the electrolytes with TAP do not increase the viscosity compared to the standard electrolyte. From a fabrication perspective, the SEB electrolytes will also add no additional cost due to the similarity in processing during and after introduction into a cell.
A distinctive feature of SEB cells is high power on demand. When batteries are not in operation, SEB cells are left idle at room temperature, exhibiting high stability and safety. However, upon operation, a SEB cell switches to high-reactivity conditions through rapid thermal stimulation. This can be illustrated through DCR, which is inversely proportional to power performance. Here, DCRs upon discharge and charge for SEB and baseline LIB cells are measured at 50% SOC by a 10-s hybrid pulse power characterization (HPPC) method. As expected, the DCR values increase substantially by adding a small amount of TAP in the electrolyte, as shown in Fig. 3 (A and B), which also demonstrates that adding more TAP in SEB-3 (e.g., 1.5 wt %) results in a further increase in DCR, owing to the formation of thicker protective layers.
Figure 3C shows the relative power of SEB cells versus the baseline LIB, where the power of the baseline cell at room temperature is normalized to be unity, thus demonstrating that SEB cells can provide sufficient, higher power by operating at higher temperatures. At 50% SOC, SEB-1 operated at 29.2°C provides the same power as the baseline cell at room temperature. The safest cell, SEB-3, with 1.5 wt % TAP additive requires an operation temperature of 44.6°C to deliver the same power as the baseline cell at room temperature. The baseline cell has a narrow temperature window of 15° to 35°C, whereas the SEB cells have much higher maximum operating temperature without becoming excessively reactive. Thus, the necessity of higher temperature operation for power recovery does not pose an issue for SEB cells. At 50% SOC, the discharge power boost over the baseline Li-ion cell is 2.05, 1.81, and 1.39 for the SEB-1, SEB-2, and SEB-3, respectively (Fig. 3C). Moreover, at the ambient temperature of 0°C, the baseline LIB cell has a relative power of 0.38, while SEB-2 has a relative power of 1.81 when operated at 60°C [it takes 30 s to heat up a cell from 0° to 60°C at a speed of 2°C/s, typical of the self-heating structure of Wang et al. (1)]. This is ~5× boost in power over the LIB cell for SEB cells working in the freezing environments. Generally, SEB cells perform independent of ambient temperatures or weather, as they are always heated up in a matter of seconds and operate at a constant elevated temperature. Although heating a cell to an elevated temperature consumes cell energy, the total deliverable energy of a cell, counterintuitively, is not reduced. As shown in fig. S3, the C/3 discharge energy was 9.62 watt-hours (Wh) for the baseline cell at room temperature and 10.15 Wh for the SEB-3 cell at 60°C. According to our previous work (1), it takes ~1% cell energy for a 10°C temperature rise, meaning that the SEB-3 cell needs 3.5% of its energy for heating from 25° to 60°C; the remaining discharge energy is thus 9.79 Wh, which is 2% higher than that of the baseline cell at room temperature.
For the baseline cell, the capacity loss at elevated temperatures is mainly due to SEI growth on the anode side and solvent oxidation on the cathode side. As a consequence, the DCR increases markedly with cycle number (Fig. 4B). In the case of SEB cells, the DCR of the fresh cell is initially much larger than the baseline cell; however, its rate of increase is much slower due to the protective coating on both the anode and cathode (Fig. 2B). Figure 4 (C and D) shows discharge curves of the fresh SEB cell versus the aged cell, respectively. Because of its DCR increase with cycle number, SEB-3 shows slight power fade after 2821 cycles at 60°C. In contrast, the baseline cell shows a drastic DCR increase and, hence, substantial power loss within only 556 cycles (fig. S6). For all the SEB cells with TAP additive, their DCRs increase linearly and increased additive content leads to higher DCR in fresh cells but slower DCR evolution with cycle number (Fig. 4B). The SEB cells do not produce gas during cycling tests, yielding more safety than the baseline cell. In addition, cells containing TAP produce less gas during formation than the baseline cell (2, 12).
Last, the SEB cells offer an important benefit associated with thermal management of a battery pack. When high power is required, the SEB cells are to be heated internally (1) and operated at elevated temperatures. Assuming the environmental temperature is 25°C, and the SEB and baseline cells operate at 60° and 30°C, respectively, the SEB provides a temperature difference driving heat dissipation that is 7× larger than the baseline case. Further, the SEB cell has lower DCR at its operational temperature of 60°C (17.1 ohm·cm2 for SEB with 1 wt % TAP) than the baseline cell at 30°C (25.3 ohm·cm2), indicating ~1.5× lower heat generation at the same current. The combination of these two factors eases the burden of thermal management by a factor of approximately 10 for SEB cells.
The electrolytes for SEB cells were formulated by reducing EC content and adding TAP as an additive. Although EC is an essential solvent for SEI layer formation, it also leads to gas generation, especially at high voltage (13). Calendar aging testing shows that high-temperature and high-SOC conditions accelerate capacity fade and increase in internal resistance while also promoting gas generation. SEB cells initially contains 10 wt % EC in the electrolyte. Some EC is consumed during the formation cycle, resulting in an EC content much less than 10% in formed SEB cells. This is advantageous since the rate of gas generation in an EC-less electrolyte would be lower than that in an electrolyte with high EC content.
There is another advantage of SEB cells promising for ultralong cycle life when deployed in the field. While conventional LIB cells undergo a large environmental temperature swing, the SEB cells almost always operate at a single, constant temperature (say 60°C) regardless of ambient temperatures and after an extremely short period of initial transition by self-heating (on the order of tens of seconds). The latter feature guarantees minimal damage of battery materials in SEB cells caused by wide temperature variations.
The stability and safety of SEB cells are further evident in high-voltage charge and high-temperature calendar life tests (figs. S1 and S2). The SEB cells can undergo 1254 exposures to high-voltage abuse [constant current (CC) charge to 4.4 V, constant voltage (CV) to C/20] at 40°C with a capacity retention of 80%, whereas the baseline cell sustains only 40 cycles at the same capacity loss and operating temperature, indicating that the SEB cell is >30× more stable and hence safer than the baseline cells under high-voltage charging conditions. Calendar life testing further shows that the passivated SEB cells can effectively suppress self-discharge. The self-discharge current is measured by holding the cell voltage constant at a required value, such as 4.187 V for 100% state of charge (SOC). Both baseline and SEB cells display a fast decrease of self-discharge current density in the beginning of calendar aging due to anode SEI layer growth. Fresh SEB cells show self-discharging currents ~5× lower than the baseline cell at room temperature and 50% SOC, 6× lower at room temperature and 100% SOC, and ~7× lower at 60°C at both 50 and 100% SOC. After 60 days of storage, the self-discharge current begins to plateau; however, the self-discharge current in the SEB cell is still 2× lower than that in the baseline cell at room temperature and 50% SOC and 3× lower at room temperature and 100% SOC. The self-discharge becomes 4× lower at high temperature (60°C) at both 50 and 100% SOC, indicating that at elevated temperatures, the SEB cells maintain superiority in calendar life over the baseline cell.
The SEM and XPS analyses were performed by first extracting the electrode samples from the fully discharged graphite/NCM622 pouch cells after cycling and washing 3× with EMC. XPS tests were conducted on a PHI VersaProbe II Scanning XPS Microprobe. The samples were loaded in a glove box and transferred into the instrument through a vacuum transfer vessel. SEM imaging was performed on an FEI Nova NanoSEM 630 SEM instrument.
One molar of LiPF6 dissolved in EC/EMC (3:7 by wt) + 2 wt % VC was used as control electrolyte (BASF). One molar of LiPF6 dissolved in a mixture of EC/EMC + 2 wt % VC was mixed in-house. To build SEB cells, 0.5 to 1.5 wt % TAP were mixed into the conventional electrolyte as additives.
We fabricated 2.8-Ah pouch cells using LiNi0.6Co0.2Mn0.2O2 (Umicore) for cathodes and graphite (Nippon Carbon) for anodes. The capacity ratio of negative to positive electrode, or NP ratio, was designed at 1.2. The 2.8-Ah pouch cell contains a stack of 20 anode and 19 cathode layers. A Celgard-2325 separator of 25 μm in thickness was used. The loadings of NMC622 on the positive electrode and graphite on the negative electrode were 10.5 and 6.6 mg/cm2, respectively.
Cycle aging tests of the pouch cells were performed using a Land instrument battery testing system (Model CT2001B, Land Instruments). A forced-air oven was used to control different ambient temperatures. For each aging cycle, the cell was charged to 4.2 V at a constant current of 2.8 A (1C-rate) and then charged at a constant voltage of 4.2 V until the current decreased to 0.14 A (C/20). After resting for 5 min, the cell was discharged to 2.8 V at a constant current of 2.8 A (1C-rate) followed by a final rest period of 5 min. When the aging cycle number reached a specific value (e.g., 403, 1006 cycles), the cell was cycled at a charge and discharge rate of C/3 to determine the capacity (designated as C/3 capacity) of the cell. For impedance tests at different temperatures, the cells were fully charged and then discharged at a rate of C/3 to 90% SOC. Impedance testing was performed with an AC voltage amplitude of 5 mV in the frequency range of 50 kHz to 0.005 Hz. For DCR test, the cells were fully charged and then discharged to 50% SOC at C/3-rate. A discharge rate of 5C and a charge rate of 3.75C were used to determine the value of DCRDischarge and DCRCharge.
For the nail penetration test, the cell was fully charged (1C CCCV charge with a cutoff voltage of 4.2 V and a cutoff current of C/20). Thermocouples were placed at 10 mm to the geometry center of the cell and at the negative tab of the cell. The nail diameter is 5 mm, made of heat-resisting steel (point angle of the nail is 60°; nail surface is clean, without rust or oil). Rate of penetration was at 30 mm/s; the nail penetrated through the geometrical center of the electrode plane perpendicularly and stayed inside the cell. The observation time was 1 hour until the cell cooled down and the cell voltage dropped to nearly zero.
The cathodes were prepared by coating an N-methyl-2-pyrrolidone-based–based slurry onto 15-μm-thick Al foil, whose dry material consists of NCM622 (91.5 wt %), Super-P (TIMCAL) (4.1 wt %), and polyvinylidene fluoride (Arkema) (4.4 wt %) as a binder. The anodes were prepared by coating deionized water–based slurry onto 10-μm-thick Cu foil, whose dry material consists of graphite (95.4 wt %), Super-P (1.0 wt %), styrene-butadiene rubber (Zeon) (2.2 wt %), and carboxymethyl cellulose (Dai-Ichi Kogyo Seiyaku) (1.4 wt %).
Calendar aging tests were performed at different ambient temperatures and SOCs. The forced-air oven was used to control different ambient temperatures. The cell voltage was kept constant, and the current was collected. When the calendar aging time reached a specific value (e.g., 25, 60, 120, and 180 days), the cell was cycled at a charge and discharge rate of C/3 to determine capacity of the cell. Then, impedance and DCR tests were conducted under the same conditions as that for the cycle-aged cells.
Each pouch cell has a 110 mm × 56 mm footprint area, weighs 63 g, and has 2.8-Ah nominal capacity with a specific energy of 166 Wh/kg and an energy density of 310 Wh per liter. Discharge performance of the baseline and SEB cells at room temperatures is shown in fig. S7 as a function of C-rate.
More broadly, the proposed strategy of passivating a battery cell for safety in idle conditions and then self-heating for high power before operation has a profound impact on future directions of battery materials development. Within the SEB framework, the high reactivity of active materials and electrolytes as well as of EEIs is no longer a requirement. The only requirement is stability at elevated temperatures. Such a design strategy will lead to dormant cell performance at low temperatures or even low power at room temperature, but all these deficiencies can be circumvented by the self-heating structure (1), which will take a SEB cell from low or room temperature to an elevated temperature suitable for high power output in tens of seconds. On the other hand, these SEB cells enjoy ultrahigh safety and ultralow degradation under all scenarios as well as robust cycling stability at elevated temperatures. We hope that this unconventional strategy will unleash a vast class of new materials for development of a disruptive generation of LIBs.
Overall, the novel SEB offers high safety and stability at idle conditions, demonstrated through mechanical (nail penetration), electrical (high-voltage charge), and thermal abuse (high-temperature storage). The stability of the SEB-2 cell under high voltage leads to 14.5% extra energy when it is charged to 4.4 V. It delivers 81% more discharge power and 65% more charge power while operating at 60°C. Furthermore, SEB-3 achieved >4000 cycles at 60°C while still showing signs of a healthy cell to continue operation. In addition, the high operational temperature facilitates thermal management. All these key advantages demonstrated here (high safety, high power on demand, long life, and easy thermal management) make SEB cells highly promising for widespread application to, e.g., the next-generation electric vehicles.
In the context of electric vehicles, introduction of the SEB yields a substantial gain in energy density and cost reduction at the pack level due to (i) simplified or entirely eliminated thermal management system; (ii) enhanced safety of SEB cells, thus enabling removal of some or all safety devices installed in a battery pack; and (iii) simplified battery management system due to SEB cells always operating at a single, constant temperature, rendering estimation of SOC, state of power, state of health, etc. oversimplified. We believe that 25 to 30% gain in energy density and 30% reduction in cost for SEB battery packs are possible without introducing new chemistry or cell manufacturing.
Rechargeable lithium-ion batteries (LIBs) are widely used in electrified vehicles, consumer electronics, and stationary energy storage systems. Simultaneous realization of high safety and high energy density/performance is a perpetual pursuit. Unfortunately, conventional batteries are passive devices where the performance, safety, and calendar/cycle life are all dictated by the electrochemical reactivity at ever-present anode/electrolyte and cathode/electrolyte interfaces. An inherent conflict between the reactivity and stability of battery materials persists at the electrode/electrolyte interfaces (EEIs). More specifically, highly reactive electrode/electrolyte materials provide high power and high performance but result in poor safety and accelerated degradation even when the battery is not in use. Highly stable (i.e., less reactive) electrode/electrolyte materials give rise to battery safety, low degradation, low self-discharge, and long life, but such materials offer low power and performance. As a result, materials development for batteries has always aimed at trade-offs of finding electrode and electrolyte materials that are not too reactive but also not too stable.
This work describes a new strategy to achieve both safe and energy-dense battery (SEB) cells, as schematically sketched in Fig. 1, where the cell resistance is plotted against the inverse of temperature. First, a passivated cell is judiciously designed and built by using highly stable materials and by creating exceptionally stable EEIs, as characterized by higher charge-transfer resistance (Rct) and higher direct-current resistance (DCR). This is illustrated in Fig. 1 by the line from point a (the conventional Li-ion cell design) to point b (the SEB cell design). It follows that these resistive SEB cells are inherently stable and safe, as demonstrated by nail penetration, short circuiting, and high-temperature storage. Second, in order for SEB cells to deliver high power during operation, they are heated instantaneously before operation, say from room temperature to 60°C, so as to recover acceptable operational DCR and ultimately battery power, going from point b (at room temperature) to point c (at an elevated temperature such as 60°C) in Fig. 1. This power on demand through rapid thermal stimulation is opposed to standby power in the present-day LIB cells, where the high-power EEIs need to be ever present. Rapid cell heating at a speed of 1° to 5°C/s has been made possible by a self-heating structure discovered by Wang et al. (1), in which a micrometer-thick nickel foil is inserted in a stack of anode-separator-cathode assemblies for uniform and internal heating. Thus, heating from room temperature to 60°C for battery operation conveniently takes only 10 to 20 s.
To achieve the requisite stable, robust EEIs, the additive, triallyl phosphate (TAP), is used in this work based on sufficient evidence in the literature of its ability to improve cell stability at both high-voltage and high-temperature conditions. For example, in 2015, Xia et al. (2) demonstrated that a TAP-based electrolyte forms thick protective layers on both electrodes in graphite/NCM442-based cells as evidenced by reduced self-discharge at high temperatures, reduced gas production during high-temperature cycling, and increased Rct. Although TAP has been explored previously, it is chosen in the present work to create resistive Li-ion cells as an example to illustrate the concept of realizing high safety and high performance simultaneously. Other ways to build resistive cells, such as using electrode materials of low Brunauer-Emmett-Teller areas, are effective as well.
In this study, we synthesized Nb-doped stabilized cubic-phase LLZO powder using the conventional solid-state reaction and prepared submicron LLZNO powder using the attrition milling process. Electrolyte ceramics prepared using submicron LLZNO powder can be sintered without mother powder, which reduces the sintering temperature and shortens the sintering time. After being sintered at 1150 °C for 60 min, the total ionic conductivity, relative density, and activation energy was 3.49 × 10−4 S·cm−1, 90.4%, and 0.316 eV, respectively. When sintered at 1200 °C for 30 min, we obtained the highest total ionic conductivity of 5.09 × 10−4 S·cm−1, the relative density was 87.3%, and the smallest activation energy was 0.311 eV. For the quasi-solid-state batteries assembled with submicron LLZNO powder, the capacity retention rate was 99.15% and the specific capacity was 105.5 mAh/g after 50 cycles at room temperature with a current density of 0.02 mA/cm2. Therefore, we have presented a simple method to reduce the waste of raw materials and energy used when sintering LLZO ceramics. At the same time, the prepared submicron LLZO powder can also be applied in quasi-solid-state batteries, with a good electrochemical performance.
In order to test the electrochemical performance of submicron LLZNO powder, we prepared a composite cathode and assembled quasi-solid-state batteries. The composite cathode consisted of a LiMn2O4 positive electrode layer and a submicron LLZNO electrolyte layer. The positive electrode was fabricated by coating the slurry of a mixture containing LiMn2O4 powder, submicron LLZNO powder, acetylene black (Shanghai Hersbit Chemical Co., Ltd., Shanghai, China), and polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF, FR905, Shanghai San ai fu New Material Technology Co., Ltd., Shanghai, China), with a weight ratio of 7:2:1:1, onto circular aluminum foils (thickness of 20 µm, Shenzhen Kejingstar Technology Ltd., Shenzhen, China) as the current collector, and the positive material loading was 1.66 mg/cm2. Then the composite cathode was fabricated by coating the slurry of a mixture containing submicron LLZNO powder and Polyvinylidene Fluoride (PVDF) with a weight ratio of 9:1 onto the positive electrode layer. The composite cathode was punched into disks with 18 mm diameters after compacted by a roller press (Shenzhen Kejingstar Technology Ltd., Shenzhen, China), and the density of composite cathode was about 2.5 g/cm3. Quasi-solid-state batteries were assembled with two electrode coin cells (type CR-2025) in a glove box filled with argon and with lithium metal foil (15 mm in diameter and 1 mm thick, Shenzhen Kejingstar Technology Ltd., Shenzhen, China) as the negative current collector. In addition, 20 µL of a liquid organic electrolyte (1 M LiPF6 dissolved in ethyl carbonate (EC) and dimethyl carbonate (DMC) with a ratio of 1:1, CAPCHEM, Shenzhen, China [45]) was added to improve the contact and reduce the interface impedance between the submicron LLZNO electrolyte layer and the anode/cathode [46,47]. Compared with lithium-ion batteries, the added amount of liquid organic electrolyte was small [48,49].
X-ray diffraction (XRD, Cu-Kα radiation, λ = 1.542 Å, Bruker D8 ADVANCE, Bruker AXS GmbH, Karlsruhe, Germany) was used to determine the phase of the ceramics pellets at room temperature within 10–60 °C with steps of 5 °C/min. Jade Software was used to match and analyze the phase of the sample. The relative density of ceramics was measured by Archimedes’ method and deionized water was used as the immersion medium. Meanwhile, the theoretical density of LLZNO, calculated by the Jade Software, was 5.20 g/cm3, and the relative density was the measured density divided by the theoretical density. The particle size and distribution of the powder were determined by the laser diffraction particle-size test method (LD, Mastersizer 3000, Malvern Instruments Limited, Malvern, UK), and the relative density, refractive index, and absorption rate of the LLZNO powder was 5.20 g/cm3, 1.4, and 0.1, respectively. The microtopography of the submicron LLZNO powder and cross section of the ceramic pellets was observed by scanning electron microscope (SEM, TESCAN MIRA3 LMU, TESCAN Orsay Holding, a. s., Brno, Czech Republic). Energy dispersive spectrometer (Oxford X-ray Max20, Oxford Instruments plc, Oxford, UK) mapping was used to characterize the distribution of each element in the cross section of the ceramic pellets. The total lithium ion conductivity of the ceramic pellets was measured by an Electrochemical Impedance Spectroscopy (EIS, Gamry Reference 600+, Gamry Instruments, Warminster, PA, USA) within a temperature range of 25–80 °C, within the frequency of 10 Hz–5 MHz, and with an AC amplitude of 40 mV. The blocking electrode was uniformly coated by a thin silver layer on both sides of the ceramic pellets. The activation energy of the ceramic pellets was measured within a temperature range of 25–80 °C and calculated based on the Arrhenius equation [16]. The quasi-solid-state batteries were tested under the battery charge‒discharge tester (BTS-5V3A, Neware Technology Co., Ltd., Shenzhen, China) at 25 °C, and current density was 0.02 mA/cm2.
A process flow chart of the preparation of submicron LLZNO powder and the sintering of LLZNO ceramics is showed in Figure 1. LLZNO powder was synthesized by the conventional solid-state reaction [44]. Lithium hydroxide monohydrate (LiOH·H2O, 98%, Xilong Scientific Co., Ltd., Shantou, China), lanthanum oxide (La2O3, 99.99%, Shanghai Aladdin Bio-Chem Technology Co., Ltd., Shanghai, China), zirconia (ZrO2, 99%, Shanghai Aladdin Bio-Chem Technology Co., Ltd., Shanghai, China), and niobium oxide (Nb2O5, 99.99%, Sinopharm Chemical Reagent Co., Ltd., Shanghai, China) were used as the raw materials and 10 wt% excess of LiOH·H2O was added to compensate for the lithium loss in the high-temperature calcination and sintering process. Yttrium stabilized zirconia (YSZ, 4~8 mm in diameter) and isopropanol (IPA) were used as the ball-grinding medium. The ratio of raw material to grinding balls was 1:5 and the mixed raw material powder was wet-ball ground at 800 rpm in the planetary ball mill for 6 h. The mixture was dried at 70 °C for 14 h, then calcined at 950 °C for 12 h in an alumina crucible with ambient air to obtain the cubic-phase LLZNO powder. LLZNO slurry was attrition milled (Shanghai ROOT mechanical and electrical equipment Co., Ltd., Shanghai, China, 0.7 L volume, 70% filling rate) at 1000 rpm for 2 h, taking YSZ (0.4 mm in diameter) and IPA as the grinding medium, and the solid‒liquid ratio was 1:5. The LLZNO slurry was dried at 70 °C for 14 h to obtain submicron LLZNO powder, from which green pellets (mass of 3 g, 19 mm in diameter and a thickness of about 4 mm) were pressed at 200 MPa under a cold uniaxial press. After that, the green pellets were sintered in a muffle furnace (Changsha Yuandong Electric Furnace Factory) without mother powder at 1100–1200 °C for 30–360 min and then cooled down naturally. At the same time, the green pellets were put on a platinum wire and placed in a crucible of MgO with the lid on to prevent impurity migration and a large amount of volatilization of lithium during the process of high-temperature sintering. For further testing, LLZNO ceramic pellets were polished with 400 and 1000 mesh sandpaper.
In this study, submicron LLZNO powder with a stable cubic phase was synthesized using the conventional solid-state reaction and prepared by the attrition milling process. The submicron LLZNO powder had a high sintering activity, which promoted the sintering process, reduced the sintering temperature and time, and reduced the loss of Li during high-temperature sintering. All these characteristics favored lithium stoichiometry and ionic conductivity. Furthermore, LLZNO ceramics were obtained without mother powder while sintering under reduced temperature and time. The particles-size distribution, phase structure, microtopography, total ionic conductivity, relative density, and activation energy were characterized and analyzed. The quasi-solid-state lithium batteries with LiMn2O4 as the positive electrode and submicron LLZNO powder as the solid electrolyte were assembled and the electrochemical performance are tested and analyzed.
Currently, lithium-ion batteries are widely used in electric vehicles (EVs), hybrid electric vehicles (HEVs), computers, smart grids, wearable devices, etc. [1]. Traditional lithium-ion batteries have organic liquid electrolytes which easily burn and explode under abusive conditions. In addition, with the development of modern society, lithium-ion batteries have gradually moved toward high specific energy. Researchers have studied cathode materials, such as LiCoO2, LiMn2O4, LiFePO4, LiNi0.6Co0.2Mn0.2O2, LiNi0.8Co0.1Mn0.1O2, LiNi0.8Co0.15Al0.05O2, and xLi2MnO3·(1 − x)LiMO2, to increase the energy density of lithium-ion batteries [2,3,4,5,6,7,8]. The energy density can be improved by increasing the charging voltage, which will lead to serious side reactions and safety issues. In order to solve the safety problem of lithium-ion batteries, researchers have turned their attention to all-solid-state lithium batteries, which use inorganic electrolytes. The non-flammability, long cycling life and wide electrochemical window of all-solid-state lithium batteries are considered to provide the high safety and high energy density of the next-generation energy storage systems [9,10].
A solid electrolyte is an important component of all-solid-state batteries. It can not only be used as a lithium ionic conductor, substituting for a liquid organic electrolyte, but also can be used to block direct contact between the positive and negative electrodes, like a separator [11]. Solid electrolytes generally contain Li3N, LiPON, perovskite, LISICON, NASICON, garnet, etc. [12,13,14,15,16,17]. Some of these solid electrolytes have high ionic conductivity (~10−3 S·cm−1). However, some issues still exist, such as instability in an ambient atmosphere (Li10GeP2S12, LGPS) and the metal cation being easily reduced by lithium (such as Ti4+ in LixLa2/3 -x/3TiO3, LLTO) [18,19]. The cubic garnet LLZO was discovered by Murugan et al. [17] in 2007 and attracted world-wide attention for its advantages, e.g., the simple preparation process, high ionic conductivity (~10−3 S·cm−1) at room temperature, high electrochemical window (0~6 V vs. Li/Li+), and electrochemical stability of lithium metal. On the other hand, LLZO also has some defects, such as an unstable cubic phase and a low density of ceramics [20,21]. Moreover, a mass of LLZO mother powder is needed to compensate for lithium loss when sintering at high temperatures [21,22]. Many solutions have been adopted to solve the above issues. For example, Al, Ga, Fe, Ta, Nb, W, Y, and Sb doping were used to stabilize the cubic phase [23,24,25,26,27,28,29,30]; hot pressing sintering, plasma sintering, and microwave sintering were adopted to improve the relative density and sintering additives [31,32,33]; and Y2O3, Al2O3, B2O3, CaO, MgO, Li3PO4, and Li4SiO4 were investigated to reduce the grain-boundary resistance [34,35,36,37,38,39,40]. Usually, in order to evaluate the electrochemical performance, LLZO was used as solid electrolyte in all-solid-state batteries [41,42,43].
AC impedance plots and the enlargement of the LLZNO ceramic pellets under different sintering conditions are showed in Figure 4a, b. The fitting curve of the sample sintered at 1200 °C for 30 min (SL2) is showed in Figure 4c, and it consists of a quasi-semicircle at high frequency and a long diffusion tail at low frequency. The equivalent circuit model Rb(RgbQgb)(RelQel), in which Rb, Rgb, and Rel are resistances originating from the bulk, grain boundaries, and Ag electrodes, is used to fit the plots and is shown in Figure 4d. The total ionic conductivity of the ceramics is mainly decided by Rb plus Rgb. The total ionic conductivity and relative density of the LLZNO ceramic pellets are showed in Figure 4e and Table 2. The highest total ionic conductivity (5.09 × 10−4 S·cm−1) of the LLZNO ceramic pellets was obtained when sintered at a high temperature and for a short time (SL2, 1200 °C × 30 min), and its relative density is 87.3%. This indicates that high-performance LLZNO ceramics are obtained when sintered at high temperatures only for short sintering times. However, the total ionic conductivity and relative density of ceramic pellets decreased and impure phases occurred when the sintering time was prolonged at 1100 and 1200 °C. The lowest total ionic conductivity (0.35 × 10−4 S·cm−1) and relative density (83.4%) were obtained when the ceramic pellets were sintered at 1100 °C for 360 min (SL5). Meanwhile, a higher total ionic conductivity (3.49 × 10−4 S·cm−1) and a higher relative density (90.3%) of ceramic pellets (SL3, 1150 °C × 60 min) were obtained when sintered for 60 min from 1100 to 1200 °C, and this result indicates that, in this study, increasing the sintering temperature too much was disadvantageous for obtaining LLZNO ceramics with good performance.
The XRD pattern of the LLZNO powder is shown in Figure 2b and was identified as cubic phase (PDF 63-0174). The LD result and SEM image of the LLZNO powder after the attrition milling process, which demonstrated a submicron powder, are showed in Figure 2a and Table 1. The D(10), D(50), D(90), and primary particle size of the submicron LLZNO powder were 0.43 µm, 0.59 µm, 0.812 µm, and about 0.1 µm, respectively. The value of D(3,2) (0.575 µm) is similar to that of D(4,3) (0.607 µm), which indicates that the prepared powder had a uniform particle-size distribution. In addition, the powder also had a higher specific surface area (2007 m2/kg), which means that the powder had a high sintering activity, which can promote crystal growth and the rapid densification of ceramics in the sintering process.
SEM images of cross sections of the LLZNO ceramics, which were sintered under different conditions, are showed in Figure 6a–e. We found that the grain size of the ceramics that were sintered for 60 min within a temperature range of 1100 to 1200 °C gradually increased from 1~5 μm (SL4, 1100 °C for 60 min, Figure 6d). A few of the grains were 5 μm and most of the grains were 100~200 μm (SL3, 1150 °C for 60 min, Figure 6c), and finally, all grains were about 200 μm (SL1, 1200 °C for 60 min, Figure 6a). Here, we found a mass of abnormal growth grains (AGGs) [50], as shown in Figure 6a,c,e, and a mass of pores were distributed in the AGGs. Meanwhile, the total ionic conductivity was lower when the AGGs were bigger. This was due to the submicron LLZNO powder having a high sintering activity, which made the crystal grain of the LLZNO ceramics have a high specific surface energy during the high-temperature sintering process, and promoted rapid grain growth and ceramic densification in the sintering process. For the above reasons, the growth rate of the grains was higher than the migration rate of the pores at the grain boundaries when the sintering temperature was higher and the sintering time was longer and the pores could not be discharged from the grain boundaries and finally stay on the inside of the AGGs. As a result, the bulk impedance of the crystal grains increased, and the total ion conductivity was reduced. However, although the submicron LLZNO powder had high sintering activity, the growth of grains could not be entirely promoted in a shorter sintering time and at a lower temperature. Therefore, a mass of grains which stayed in the initial state are shown in Figure 6d (SL4, 1100 °C × 60 min), and this was disadvantageous for lithium-ionic conduction due to the incomplete surface of the LLZNO grains after the attrition milling process. Eventually, the ceramic pellets showed a lower total ionic conductivity (0.51 × 10−4 S·cm−1). A cross-sectional SEM image of the sample sintered at 1200 °C for 30 min (SL2) is showed in Figure 6b. It was found that the grains grew uniformly (~4 μm), their surfaces were smooth without pores, and they bond tightly with other grains. A highest ionic conductivity of 5.09 × 10−4 S·cm−1 was obtained, which indicates that the submicron LLZNO powder had a higher sintering activity and high total ionic conductivity LLZNO ceramic pellets could be obtained by sintered at a high temperature for only a short time. At the same time, the LLZNO ceramic pellets which had a higher total ionic conductivity could also be also obtained when the sintering temperature was properly reduced.
The specific capacity and coulombic efficiency of quasi-solid-state batteries with LiMn2O4 as the positive electrode after 50 cycles of a galvanostatic charge‒discharge test at 25 °C are showed in Figure 7a. The 1st, 2nd, 10th, 20th, and 50th galvanostatic charge‒discharge curves of quasi-solid-state batteries are showed in Figure 7b. The quasi-solid-state batteries showed good cycling performance at a current density of 0.02 mA/cm2 and a voltage within 3.0–4.3 V. The first discharge specific capacity was 106.4 mAh/g and the coulomb efficiency was 93.23%. The 2nd, 10th, 20th, and 50th discharge specific capacities were 106.8 mAh/g, 105.3 mAh/g, 106.9 mAh/g, and 105.5 mAh/g, respectively. After 50 cycles of the galvanostatic charge‒discharge test, the coulomb efficiency was maintained at about 95% and the capacity retention rate was 99.15%. The capacity of the batteries increased in the early stage of the galvanostatic charge‒discharge test, which may be caused by the activation of positive material. This indicates that submicron LLZNO powder can be used in quasi-solid-state batteries, and that the specific capacity and the cycling stability of quasi-solid-state batteries are relatively good. Here, the electrochemical performance of quasi-solid-state batteries using submicron LLZNO powder is only discussed, and further research will be carried out in the future.
The XRD patterns of the LLZNO ceramic samples are showed in Figure 3. The phases of all the prepared ceramic samples were identified as cubic phases (PDF 63-0174). The crystal parameters of the different samples are showed in Table 2. The XRD patterns of the samples sintered at 1200 °C × 60 min (SL1) and at 1100 °C × 360 min (SL5) showed a few impure phase peaks, mainly belonging to LiNbO3 (PDF 82-0459) and Li7NbO6 (PDF 29-0816), and due to the decomposition from the high sintering activity of the LLZNO after having been sintered for too long at a high temperature. Moreover, these impure phases decreased the total ionic conductivity of LLZNO ceramics by increasing the resistance of the grain boundary.
Figure 6f shows the SEM image and its EDS mapping, including La, Zr, and Nb in the cross section of the LLZNO ceramic of 1200 °C × 30 min (SL2). The cross section of the sample exhibits a transgranular fracture and an intergranular fracture, and the elements of La, Zr, and Nb are relatively uniformly distributed, which indicates that the Nb element was successfully incorporated into the LLZO lattice. This is also verified by the XRD result. However, the non-uniform distribution of Zr, La, and Nb exists in the central part of the EDS mapping. This indicates that during high-temperature sintering element segregation and depletion occurred due to the different migration rates of the elements. 
Arrhenius plots and the linear fitting curve are showed in Figure 5a. The activation energy of ceramics samples is showed in Figure 5b and Table 2, and their values are within the range of 0.31–0.33 eV. This indicates that there was no obvious effect on the activation energy of the ceramics when the green pellets prepared from the submicron LLZNO powder were sintered. The variation tendency of the activation energy was similar to the total ionic conductivity, and the lowest and the highest activation energy was 0.311 eV (SL2, 1200 °C × 30 min) and 0.328 eV (SL5, 1100 °C × 360 min).
The research leading to these results was funded by the Romanian EEA Research Programme operated by MEN under the EEA Financial Mechanism 2009–2014, project contract No. 1SEE/2014. We also thank the Norwegian Research council for its financial support, and Bioing. A. Diaconu for the DLS measurements.
* mg·GAE/g·DW (mg of gallic acid equivalent per g dry weight).
NA—not applicable.
* The bold numbers in Table 3 indicate values within the limits of the standards; italic numbers are below the limits, while the underlined are over the limits, the bracket showing the closest limits in the standard. ** ORAC—oxygen radical absorption capacity; expressed as μmol Trolox equivalent (TE) at 100 g, accuracy of ±5%, as presented in the literature [26,27].
Concerning the antioxidant activity, the IC50 of the analyzed essential oils is in the μg/mL range that is assigned to a very good antioxidant activity which varies in the following order: clove oil > thyme oil > rosemary oil > tee tree oil, and the clove oil exhibits the highest radical scavenging activity.
Based on GC-MSD/FID analysis, it has been established that the commercially available thyme, rosemary, clove, and tea tree essential oils correspond to AFNOR/ISO standards.
On the basis of the obtained results, it can be concluded that these essential oils can be suitable alternatives to chemical additives, satisfying the consumer demand for naturally preserved food products and ensuring their safety at the same time.
The results of this study demonstrate the potential of thyme oil, clove oil, and tea tree oil for use as antifungal agents against tested fungi strains (Fusarium graminearum G87, Penicillium corylophilum CBMF1, and Aspergillus brasiliensis ATCC 16404) and three potential pathogenic food bacteria: Staphylococcus aureus, Escherichia coli, and Listeria monocytogenes. The overall results of the MIC values show that thyme oil is the most effective with a very low concentration used against both on the three fungi and bacteria, followed by clove and tea tree oils, while the rosemary oil is less active or inactive.
Promising results were obtained by their incorporation into chitosan emulsions and films, with potential applications in food packaging that will be detailed in a future paper. Taking into account their biological activity in addition, it is expected that their use can also benefit consumers’ health.
Each of the above-mentioned constituents contributes to beneficial or adverse effects; therefore, it is very important to know as much as possible about the composition and properties of EOs, with each study bringing new highlights on the advantages and disadvantages they offer.
Consumers demand high quality foods with minimal changes in nutritional properties. A minimal amount of synthetic additives combined with a suitable packaging technology that retains or creates desirable food qualities or reduces undesirable changes in food due to microbial activity is therefore a goal of food manufacturers [1]. New processes must be designed to meet the required food product safety or shelf-life demands, and additional hurdles for microorganisms should be introduced. World Health Organization (WHO) reports [2] in recent years estimate that 30% of people in industrialized countries suffer from a food-borne disease each year. Reducing or eliminating food-borne pathogens via “green” consumerism concomitantly with low salt consumption to diminish the incidence of cardiovascular diseases is increasingly becoming a public health concern. On the other hand, antimicrobial resistance affects all areas of health, as many medicinal procedures are related to antibiotics [3].
Consumers are worried about the presence of chemical preservatives, which can lead to benzoic acid by the decarboxylating action of some spoilage microorganisms, and this is considered the cause of many carcinogenic and teratogenic attributes and residual toxicity. Therefore, the studies to find natural and socially acceptable preservatives receive increasing attention by screening the composition and the biological, antimicrobial, and antioxidant activities of plant extracts [17]. Essential oils can prevent fungal growth in food products, which may cause spoilage and result in a reduction in the quality and quantity of food (shelf-life). Most EOs applied directly onto food or in the vapor phase can reduce or stop the colony forming ability of molds. They are also regarded as safe (GRAS) and are accepted by the FDA and by consumers. By their potential antimicrobial/antifungal/antioxidant effects, EOs could be the answer to the current search for environmental solutions and to assuring the microbial safety of food products in active packaging applications [18,19].
Therefore, new methods and additives should be found to prolong service life and to improve the safety of foods. Recently, effective preventive measures and intelligent preservation methods have been put into place to reduce food spoilage, increase safety, and prolong food shelf-life. One of these methods is bioactive packaging by the use of natural compounds with multifunctional properties both to achieve the protection of food and to improve the health of consumers. The concern regarding safety issues of the synthetic antimicrobial agents has led to the use of essential oils (EOs), which represent eco-friendly alternatives to chemicals. Essential oils (also called volatile oils) are oily liquids obtained from plant materials (flowers, buds, seeds, leaves, twigs, bark, herbs, wood, fruits, and roots). Plant-derived essential oils are complex mixtures of natural volatile compounds resulting from the plant secondary metabolism and extracted from vegetable materials by expression (i.e., “cold pressing”), fermentation, enfleurage, or extraction, but the method of distillation with water or steam is the most commonly used for the commercial production of EOs. Essential oils contain important classes of compounds such as monoterpenes (C10 hydrocarbons based on 2 isoprene units), phenylpropanoides (C6 aromatic compounds with C3 side chains), sesquiterpenes (C15 hydrocarbons based on 3 isoprene units), diterpenes (C20), triterpenes (C30) and their oxygenated derivatives, and phenolic compounds (such as thymol and carvacrol). Due to their versatile content, essential oils constitute a rich source of biologically active compounds possessing antimicrobial, antibacterial, antifungal, antioxidant, antiviral, antimycotic, antitoxigenic, antiparasitic, antibiotic, and antiseptic properties and insecticidal activities; therefore, they are useful in a wide range of applications [4,5].
In this study, four essential oils, namely, thyme (Thymus vulgaris L.), clove (Eugenia caryophyllus from dried floral buds of Syzygium aromaticum), rosemary (Rosmarinus officinalis L.), and tea tree (Melaleuca alternifolia aetheroleum) obtained from Romanian production (Fares Co., Orăştie, Romania) are intent to be used as components in bioactive food packaging. Therefore, as a first step, it should be worthwhile to comparatively evaluate the composition and antimicrobial/antioxidant activity of these four EOs. Antifungal and antibacterial activity against three target food spoilage fungi (Aspergillus brasiliensis, Fusarium graminearum, and Penicillium corylophilum) and three potential pathogenic food bacteria (S. aureus, E. coli, and L. monocytogenes) have been evaluated. The minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) concentration was established in each case. The antioxidant activity was determined, and the most efficient oil for each type of activity was established. Preliminary tests on the EO encapsulation into chitosan films and their antimicrobial activity against the spoilage of beef meat showed promising results, a detailed presentation for which will be provided in a future paper.
There are many studies on the characterization of volatile compound composition and the antimicrobial and antioxidant activities of various selected groups of essential oils. Bozin et al. characterized Lamiaceae species and the antimicrobial and antioxidant activities of the oils of Ocimum basilicum L., Origanum vulgare L., and Thymus vulgaris L. [6], and the chemical constituents of four populations of Piper aduncum L. from Distrito Federal, Brazil [7], were identified. Many other essential oils have been characterized, namely, sweet lime (Citrus limetta Risso) [8], Chenopodium ambrosioides, Philodendron bipinnatifidum [9], cinnamon oil, eucalyptus oil, lemongrass oil, peppermint oil, citronella oil, turpentine oil [10], citronella oil [11], Tithonia diversifolia (Hemsl.) A. Gray [12], O. basilicum L. from Italy [13], and Iranian geranium oil [14]. The composition of two species of mint (Mentha suaveolens Ehrh. and Mentha rotundifolia) grown in Orăştie-Romania has been comparatively examinated [15]. From the 21 plant essential oils (cinnamon, clove, geranium, lemon, lime, orange and rosemary, aniseed, eucalyptus, and camphor) tested against six bacterial species four Gram-negative bacteria (Escherichia coli, Klebsiella pneumoniae, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, and Proteus vulgaris) and two Gram-positive bacteria Bacillus subtilis and Staphylococcus aureus [16], 19 oils showed antibacterial activity.
It can be observed that the surfaces are very smooth, and, by essential oil incorporation, very small particles are evidenced at high magnification. The good homogeneity of the films and the encapsulation of the oils is assured by the presence of a nonionic surfactant and emulsifier T80.
The stability of the chitosan/essential oil emulsions was sustained by dynamic light scattering (DLS) analysis, which showed a main particle population with low dimensions (Figure 11), with the distribution showing, in the low dimension range, a single peak and a polydispersity index (PDI)-approached value of 1.0 (Table 7). The chitosan/essential oil emulsions contain two kinds of particle populations: the first one is very small, where d = 5 nm for the chitosan solution and 11–70 (350) nm for the emulsion containing EOs, and the second contains larger particles of 850 nm for CS and 2500–8800 nm for CS/EOs emulsions. Oils are probably concentrated around CS particles because of aggregation.
Scanning electron microscopy examination reveals the morphology of the films obtained by the incorporation of essential oils into chitosan films—Figure 12. The films are relatively homogeneous, and dispersion of the essential oil in the film obtained by solvent casting is homogeneous, as is evident from the SEM images taken at high magnification (2000×).
The encapsulation of active (antimicrobial and antioxidant) essential oils into the chitosan matrix leads to a significant decrease in the total number of germs for beef meat packed in such films—from 2400–1020 CFU/cm2 for films containing only CS to 700 CFU/cm2 for films containing both CS and clove oil. These films proved to have a good antimicrobial activity for delaying the spoilage of beef meat, with both antimicrobial agents acting synergistically [56]. This research will be the topic of the subsequent paper.
Thyme essential oil is strongly antimicrobial, antifungal, antiviral, antiparasitic, mainly due to the high content of thymol [49]. This is in accordance with other studies that reported that thyme essential oil is efficient against Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria [29,30] and fungi [28,51,52].
The antibacterial effect of EOs against the growth of S. aureus, E. coli, and L. monocytogenes was established by the agar disc diffusion method, and the results are presented in Figure 8. On Mueller–Hinten (MH) agar plates, the inhibition zones of S. aureus are 64.7 ± 1.2 mm for thyme oil, 27.8 ± 3.4 mm for tea tree oil, 27.8 ± 4.0 mm for clove oil, and 12.8 ± 4.3 mm for rosemary oil. For E. coli, the inhibition zones are 35.5 ± 4.6 mm for thyme oil, 27.0 ± 3.4 mm for tea tree oil, 19.5 ± 0.5 mm for clove oil, and 15.1 ± 0.5 mm for rosemary oil. The diameters of the inhibition zones in the case of L. monocytogenes growth are of 69.5 ± 6.4 mm for thyme oil, 22.0 ± 2.8 mm for tea tree oil, and 28.5 ± 2.1 mm for clove oil. There is no inhibition zone for rosemary.
The inhibition zones observed after 24 h were stable and identical after 48 and 72 h of incubation. EOs are less effective in the vapor disc diffusion method compared to the disc diffusion method. Thyme and clove oils had volatile components that had inhibition zones even when the disc with EO had no contact with the bacteria. Thyme had the best effect for all test microorganisms, while clove only had an effect on S. aureus (Table 5).
TTO has gained attention in the food industry for its antimicrobial [41,42] and antifungal activity [43], and it was successfully used in respiratory or genito-urinary tract infections [44].
Thyme oil had the highest inhibition zones for the three test strains, followed by tea tree oil, and then by clove oil. Rosemary oil was the least active.
The minimal inhibitory concentration of an antimicrobial agent is the lowest (i.e., minimal) concentration of the antimicrobial agent that inhibits a given bacterial isolate from multiplying and producing visible growth in the test system. This concentration was determined by incubating a known quantity of bacteria with specified dilutions of the antimicrobial agent. Using a similar broth dilution method, Zhang et al. [53] found that MIC was 1.0 mg/mL of cinnamon for both S. aureus and E. coli. Broth microdilution is the most widely used method in clinical laboratories, but agar diffusion is also used. Due to the oily content of EOs, using solvents is needed to obtain homogeneous dilutions. The results obtained using three solvents namely Tween-20, DMSO, and ethanol by the two test methods (agar MIC testing and the broth microdilution test) are shown in Table 6. There are some differences between the test results, but they all showed that thyme is the most effective EO, with a very low concentration needed to inhibit the growth of S. aureus and E. coli, followed by clove and tea tree oils. The thyme oil MIC values with the broth dilution method was approximately 0.39%–3.13% for S. aureus and 1.56%–3.13% for E. coli. Similarly, clove MIC value range were approximately 3.13%–6.26% for S. aureus and 6.25% for E. coli. A strong antimicrobial activity of thyme was also found by Mith et al. [54] when they tested different EOs and determined MIC against both food-borne pathogens and spoilage bacteria with a broth dilution method. The MIC value ranges of tea tree oil were approximately 0.80%–25.00% for S. aureus and 12.5%–25.00% for E. coli.
Due to its antimicrobial, antifungal, antivermin, and antiviral activity [34,35], clove essential oil is used as a preservative but also exhibits other effects with positive impacts on consumer health, including antiseptic, antihelmintic, anti-inflammatory, antispastic, carminative, anti-neuralgic, antiulcer, anti-thrombotic, anticancerinogenic, and anticoagulant activities. Moreover, it acts as a local analgesic [36].
The results obtained by the ABTS method—Figure 9—are well correlated with those obtained by 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH)—Figure 10.
For the analyzed essential oils, IC50 is in the μg/mL range assigned to a very good antioxidant activity [55]. From the selected essential oils, the clove oil is by far the most radical scavenging active, with an IC50 of 8 μg/mL. The antioxidant activity was associated with the presence of phenolic compounds in the composition of essential oils, as determined by the Folin–Ciocâlteu method and the GC-FID technique and ORAC values. The antioxidant activity varies in the following order: clove oil > thyme oil > rosemary oil >> tea tree oil. Based on the radical scavenging tests, the clove oil is the most effective antioxidant is recommended for further such applications.
The results evidenced that the most effective essential oil from the tested oils was thyme essential oil, which displayed strong antifungal activity with MIC values between 116.27 and 174.41 ppm. MIC values of clove, rosemary, and tea tree essential oils were found within the range of 465.11–1395.34 ppm.
The minimum inhibitory concentrations of the tested essential oils (EOs of thyme, clove, rosemary, and tea tree oils) are presented in Table 4.
The data presented in Table 4 shows that, from all the essential oils tested in this study, rosemary oil did not show desirable results against the selected fungi.
Table 3 shows the quantitative composition (based on Gas Chromatographz with Flame Ioniyation Detector (GC-FID) of the analyzed essential oils. The GC-FID analysis was performed on several different samples obtained from the same company, i.e., Fares, Orăştie-Romania, and no relevant difference was found between them. The results are reproducible.
Sánchez-González et al. [33,40] established that the essential oil of Melaleuca alternifolia, also known as tea tree essential oil (TTO) is composed of terpene, mainly monoterpenes, sesquiterpenes, and tertiary alcohols [33,40,41,42,43]. The main components of TTO are terpineol, cineol, pinen, and terpinen and demonstrated antimicrobial activity [40,44].
The ORAC index shows the antioxidant capacity of the oils. According to databases, the antioxidant capacity is highest for clove essential oil, followed at a high distance by thyme oil, while the antioxidant capacity for tea tree is smaller than those of other essential oils. These statements are in accordance with results obtained by the Folin–Ciocâlteu method.
Most of the obtained results related to the composition of the studied essential oils are in accordance with those found by other authors and constitute support for the explanation of their potential biological activity spectrum [28,29,30,31,32,33,34,35,36,37,38,39,40,41,42,43,44]. Thyme essential oil (TEO) is obtained from Thymus vulgaris L. and exhibits antimicrobial effects due to its constituents. Omidbeygi et al. [28] found that the major compounds of TEO are thymol, carvacrol with similar chemical structures, linalool, and ρ-cymene [28,29]. The presence of thymol (2-Isopropyl-5-methylphenol) and carvacrol enhanced the TEO antimicrobial activity [30,31,32]. Clove essential oil (Caryophylli aetheroleum) (CEO) isolated from the dry floral buds of Syzygium aromaticum, belonging to the Myrtaceae family has been used for its antimicrobial activity. Goni [33], Shao [34], and Sebaaly [35] established that the CEO is composed mainly of phenylpropanoides such as eugenol, β-caryophyllene, and the eugenyl acetate [33,34,35,36].
The composition of the four essential oils is within the limits of AFNOR (Association French Normalization Organization Regulation)/ISO standards [21,22,23,24,25], except for a few differences, which could be considered within the error limits of the analysis. Deviation in the composition from standard values may not interfere with the therapeutic properties of the essential oils; however, if oils respect the standard limits, it is safer to consider them usable according to the general practice.
Jiang et al. [37] found that the rosemary essential oil (Rosmarinus officinalis L.) (REO) can be used in the food industry as a flavoring agent and preservative because of its antimicrobial and antioxidant properties [37]. Among the terpenes found in the composition of REO, the main components are the following: cineole, camphor, α-pinene, camphene, and α-terpineol [38,39].
Based on the gas chromatography analysis coupled with mass spectrometry and flame ionisation detectors, the commercial essential oils of thyme (Thymus vulgaris L.), clove (Eugenia caryophyllus), rosemary (Rosmarinus officinalis L.), and tea tree (Melaleuca alternifolia aetheroleum) were found to have compositions within the limits of the AFNOR/ISO standards.
The essential thyme oil contains especially thymol, p-cymene, γ-terpinene, linalol, isothymol (carvacrol/biosol), and β-myrcene—Figure 1.
The composition (including both main components and those in low amount but with significant biological/therapeutic effects) of the essential oils varies depending on the geographical position, the plant’s origin and species, harvest time, distillation/extraction procedure, etc. [17]. Additionally, the composition of the essential oils and consequently their biological/therapeutic activities depend on the combination and ratio of their numerous different components. Gas chromatography coupled with mass spectrometry (GC-MSD) and flame ionization (GC-FID) detectors was used to determine the quality and quantity of chemical compounds in the essential oils.
The rosemary oil is rich in light monoterpenes, containing mainly eucalyptol, camphor, α-/β-pinene, camphene, borneol, and limonene—Figure 3.
The main classes of compounds identified in the studied essential oils are presented in Table 2. Under the mentioned analysis parameters, only volatile compounds up to the level of sesquiterpenes were detected.
The chromatograms of studied essential oils are shown in Figure 1, Figure 2, Figure 3 and Figure 4.
The tea tree essential oil contained both light monoterpenes and numerous sesquiterpenes. The main compound is 4-terpineol, followed by γ-terpinene, 2-carene, α-terpineol, α-terpinene, α-pinene, o-cymene, limonene, β-caryophyllene, eucalyptol, and β-myrcene—Figure 4. Standards ask for α-terpinene (5%–13%), which was not found in our tee tree sample, instead 2-carene was found in high amounts of about 10%. Aromadendrene and δ-cadinene, mentioned by standards in amounts varying from traces up to 7%–8% were confirmed in the studied sample.
The clove essential oil had the simplest composition, based on eugenol/eugenol acetate and β-/α-caryophyllene, accompanied by several other sesquiterpenes—Figure 2.
The phenolic content of extracts of many plants contributes significantly to their total antioxidant activity. The antioxidant feature of the investigated essential oils was determined by the phenolic compouds presence in their composition by the Folin–Ciocâlteu method [20].
The total concentration of phenolic compounds found in essential oil samples are presented in Table 1, and a decrease in phenolic content concentration in the following order was found: clove > thyme > tea tree > rosemary. Excepting the rosemary oil, all oils were found to have different phenolic levels, ranging from 0.034 to 1.136 mg·GAE/g·DW, which can play a vital role in the increase of food shelf-life. The clove oil has the highest content of phenolic compounds.
The antifungal activity of the essential oils against the three fungi strains examined was assessed by the percentage of the inhibition rate (IR%) and minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC). In order to evaluate the quantity of essential oils needed to be used, a preliminary investigation was carried out with a volume of 10 µL and 20 µL of each of them. After this screening, the maximum concentration used was 60 µL, while the minimum volume used was 2.5 µL. The results presented in Figure 5, Figure 6 and Figure 7 for the antifungal activity of the essential oils tested are the ones from the 7th day of analyses. From all tested oils, the most effective were the essential oils of clove, thyme, and tea tree. The efficacy of these essential oils can be attributed to the terpenes and phenylpropanoides present in their composition. The research studies demonstrated that phenolic compounds are responsible for the antifungal potential of these oils.
The effectiveness of thyme oil as an antifungal agent can be noticed from the data presented in Figure 6. As can be seen, thyme essential oil is more active than clove essential oil, showing an inhibition rate of 100% at 10 µL, while clove oil was less effective (IR = 47.6%) at a volume of 10 µL. As well, tea tree essential oil has antifungal properties, but when a higher oil volume is used. It produced an inhibition of 89.04% for a quantity of 40 µL. It is considered that the antifungal activity of tea tree oil was significantly affected by the presence of high content of γ-terpinene (16.3%), 4-terpineol (38.7%), and α-terpineol (4.6%). Previous studies showed that tea tree oil has antifungal activity against Botrytis cinerea and Rhizopus stolonifer under in vitro conditions, inhibiting the spore germination and mycelial growth [43].
Penicillium corylophilum is a fungus that may cause the spoilage of bakery products; for this judgment, the essential oils selected were used to determine their antifungal activity against this mold.
Figure 6 shows the inhibition manifested by the tested essential oils against Penicillium corylophilum growth.
For the highest volume used in this study (60 µL), rosemary oil did not inhibit the fungal growth of Penicillium corylophilum CBMF1, the IR being below 10%.
The essential oil of rosemary showed an inhibition rate of 14.22% for the volume of 60 µL. Jiang et al. [37] tested the antimicrobial activity of rosemary essential oil and its main components, α-pinene and 1.8-cineole, against Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria and fungi (Candida albicans, Aspergillus niger). This study showed that the antimicrobial activity of rosemary essential oil was superior to its active compounds, and the essential oil is more active against all the bacteria used in this research compared to the tested fungi, concluding that the synergism between its compounds determine the antifungal activity.
Aspergillus brasiliensis is a black mold that can spoil food products, especially fruits and vegetables [48].
Comparing antifungal activity results of the studied essential oils, the following decreasing order of activity is evident: thyme oil > clove oil > tea tree oil >> rosemary oil. Concerning the sensitivity to various fungi, the thyme oil and tea tree oil are very effective in the inhibition of the Aspergillus brasiliensis, as is clove oil in the inhibition of the Penicillium corylophilum. The rosemary oil is less effective as an antifungal agent but shows some activity against Aspergillus brasiliensis. However, other studies have evidenced that high-quality rosemary oil has antitumor, antifungal, and antiparasitic effects [49]. It has also analgesic, anticancer, anticatarrhal, anti-infection, anti-inflammatory, and expectorant properties and stimulates the circulatory system [50].
The inhibition rate of the tested essential oils (thyme oil, clove oil, rosemary oil, tea tree oil) against Aspergillus brasiliensis ATCC 16404 is presented in Figure 7. The results presented evidenced that thyme oil was effective against A. brasiliensis ATCC 16404 at a volume of 5 µL (IR = 97.43%), while clove oil shows antifungal activity at a volume of 30 µL (IR = 82.64%). The strong antifungal activity of thyme oil is attributed to phenolic compounds carvacrol (2.75%) and thymol (43.1%), while the antimicrobial effectiveness of clove oil is associated with the activity of eugenol (85.7%), β-caryophyllene (4.5%), and eugenol acetate (7.9%). Similar studies were conducted by Abbaszadeh et al. [46], who tested the antifungal efficiency of thymol, carvacrol, eugenol, and menthol on growth inhibition of some important food-borne pathogens. The results showed that thymol and carvacrol inhibited the fungal growth of Cladosporium spp., Aspergillus spp., Fusarium oxysporum, Botrytis cinerea, Penicillium spp., Alternaria alternata, and Rhizopus oryzae, and the inhibition growth was dependent on the concentration used.
Tea tree essential oil inhibited the growth of the tested fungus with an inhibition rate of 88.90% for a volume of 35 µL.
The fungal growth inhibition induced by essential oils, as determined by the disc diffusion assay, was dependent mostly on the volume (varying from 5 µL to 60 µL) and nature of the essential oils. According to the results presented in Figure 5, it can be noticed that the essential oils tested had antifungal activity against Fusarium graminearum G87, but their efficacy is different. Thyme essential oil was the most effective, with an inhibition rate of over 80% at the lowest volume of essential oil used for the growth inhibition of this fungus, namely, 87.04% for 7 µL. Clove oil was also effective against the tested fungus, with an inhibition rate of 81.64% when using 40 µL. It is assumed that the high antifungal potential of clove essential oil is due to its active principle, eugenol (85.7%). The results are in accordance with the study of Abbaszadeh et al. [46] regarding the effectiveness of eugenol against pathogenic fungi, which demonstrated that this phenylpropanoide had antifungal activity against all tested fungi. The antifungal activity was in direct ratio with the concentration of eugenol added to the media. In a study made by Marin et al. [47] who tested the efficacy of cinnamon, clove, oregano, palmarosa, and lemongrass oils against the mycotoxines produced by Fusarium graminearum, it was shown that clove essential oils was the most efficient against zearalenone and deoxynivalenol release.
Fusarium graminearum, being a plant pathogen, is a fungus commonly found in cereal grains (mostly wheat and barley). This pathogen has the potential to produce mycotoxines (deoxynivalenol and zearalonene) that have a negative impact on human and animal health [45]. The contamination of cereals by this toxigenic mold produces major economic impacts in agriculture.
The essential oils selected were tested against Fusarium graminearum, and the results are presented in Figure 5.
Rosemary essential oil exhibits antifungal activity, but this was very low. For a volume of 60 µL of this oil, the inhibition was below 10%. Tea tree essential oil had an inhibition rate higher than 80% against F. graminearum G87 only for the highest volume used in this study (60 µL).
The DLS analysis of the oils-in-chitosan emulsions was carried out using a Zetasizer NS (Malvern Instruments Ltd., Malvern, UK), according with standard ISO 13321 (1996). This analysis only gives a mean particle size (z-average) and an estimate of the width of the distribution (polydispersity index (PDI)). It is very sensitive to the presence of aggregates due to the inherent intensity weighting. The oil/chitosan ratio was kept at 0.75 mL/1 g chitosan. For DLS, the concentration of the initial solution was 1.5 wt % chitosan and the corresponding concentration of the oils. The chitosan/essential oil emulsions of 1.5 wt % were diluted three times prior to analysis with the 5 wt % acetic acid aqueous solution.
The three tested bacterial strains were obtained from the Culture Collection at the University of Gothenburg: Staphylococcus aureus CCUG 1828, Escherichia coli CCUG 10979, and Listeria monocytogenes CCUG 15527. A test culture was prepared by growth on MH agar overnight, and colonies were diluted to a 0.5 McFarland in MH broth.
Three food-related fungi were used as target microorganisms in this study: Aspergillus brasilliensis ATCC 16404, Penicillium corylophilum CBMF1, and Fusarium graminearum G87, and they were provided from the collection of Faculty of Biotechnology of University of Agronomic Sciences and Veterinary Medicine Bucharest (Bucharest, Romania).
To evaluate the antifungal activity of the tested essential oils, the selected fungi were grown on a Potato Dextrose Agar (PDA, Scharlau Microbiologi, Barcelona, Spain) medium in 90 mm Petri dishes for 7–9 days and stored at 25 °C. Fungal spore suspension was obtained in aseptic conditions in a laminar flow cabinet after ultraviolet sterilization for 20 min. Fungal spore suspensions were collected from the surface of fungal colonies by gentle scraping with a sterile inoculation loop and suspended in 10 mL of sterile water. Spore population was counted using a hemocytometer (Thoma camera, 0, 100 mm depth, from Hirschmann Techcolor, Eberstadt, Germany). The concentration of spore suspensions was 106 spores/mL.
The protocol of the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI) [67,68] was followed with some modifications. The bacterial suspensions were diluted to a McFarland standard of 0.5 (0.5 McFarland standard is prepared by mixing 0.05 mL of 1.175% barium chloride dihydrate (BaCl2·2H2O), with 9.95 mL of 1% sulfuric acid (H2SO4), and adjusted to about 104–105 bacteria/mL before use. A 0.1 mL portion from this bacterial dilution was spread on Mueller–Hinten (MH) agar (MHA, Sigma-Aldrich, Darmstadt, Germany). Subsequently, sterile paper discs (Macherey-Nagel, Düren, Germany, LOT: 141112) 6 mm in diameter were placed within 15 min onto the inoculated agar surface containing 10 µL of the essential oil or 10 µL of sterile water as control. Petri dishes were incubated at 37 °C for 24 ± 1 h. After incubation, the inhibition zones were measured as the complete inhibition in mm, as a diameter including the disc. The inhibition zones were measured in triplicate with a vernier caliper. The distance from the colonies closest to the disc to the center of the disc was doubled to obtain a diameter.
The inhibition concentration of four essential oils (thyme, clove, rosemary, and tea tree) and the stability of natural antioxidant at different concentrations were evaluated using 2,2’-azino-bis 3-ethylbenzthiazoline-6-sulfonic acid (ABTS) and 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) radical methods.
The DPPH radical scavenging assay for essential oils was measured using the 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) radical. The DPPH is a stable free radical with a violet color that, under the action of proton-donating compounds, is reduced to a light yellow color, and this change can be monitored at 517 nm [71]. Concentrations of the methanolic solution between 0.156 and 20 mg/mL were tested.
The radical scavenging activity was calculated according to the following equation:
(3)%RSA=100×(Acontrol−AsampleAcontrol)
where Asample represents the absorbance of the sample solution in the presence of DPPH, and Acontrol is the absorbance of the standard DPPH solution. For more details, see ref. [72].
The ABTS•+ scavenging test is used to determine the antioxidant activity of both hydrophilic and hydrophobic compounds. ABTS•+ is generated by mixing 2.5 mL of 7 mM ABTS with 2.5 mL of 14.7 mM potassium persulfate (KPS) water solutions and stored in the dark at room temperature for 16 h. The reaction between ABTS•+ and potassium persulfate directly generates the blue green ABTS•+ chromophore, which can be reduced by an antioxidant, thereby resulting in a loss of absorbance at 750 nm.
The antioxidant capacity is expressed as percentage inhibition, calculated using the following formula [70]:
(2)Inhibition(%)=[Acontrol−AsampleAcontrol×100]
where Acontrol is the absorbance of the ABTS radical in methanol, and Asample is the absorbance of an ABTS radical solution mixed with the sample. All determinations were performed in triplicate.
The preparation of agar, broth, and bacteria were carried out as described in Section 3.7. MICs was determined for thyme, clove, and tea tree against S. aureus and E. coli according to the method used by Zhang and Mith [53,54] with some minor modifications. The original solution of each EO was dissolved in Tween-20 (0.5%), dimethyl sulfoxide (DSMO, 5%), or ethanol (100%) in a 1:1 ratio to make serial 2-fold dilutions, yielding solutions with a gradient from 100% oil to 0.2% oil (v/v). A volume of 10 µL of each oil dilution was added to the 6 mm paper disc and then placed on MH agar plates with a 100 µL bacterial concentration containing a 104–105 CFU/mL suspension of each tested bacterium. DSMO without bacteria was used as a control.
Similar dilutions in either Tween-20 (0.5%), dimethyl sulfoxide (DSMO, 5%), or ethanol (100%) were transferred to sterile microtiter plates (honeycomb plates with 100 wells). Three parallel dilution series were used with 100 µL in each well. The microtiter plates were mounted in a Bioscreen C (Oy Growth Curves Ab Ltd., Helsinki, Finland), an automated growth curve analysis system, programmed to measure absorbance at 600 nm (abs 600 nm) at regular time intervals at 37 ± 0.1 °C. Prior to each measurement, the plates were shaken for 10 s (default setting). Growth curves of both strains were recorded. Time-to-detection (TTD) were defined as ABS600nm = 0.2. Lack of absorbance above 0.2 were defined as growth inhibition.
MH-agar plate surfaces inoculated with E. coli and S. aureus and Tryptone Soya Agar (TSA, CM 0131, Oxoid Ltd., Thermo Fisher Scientific, Basingstoke, Hampshire, UK) with L. monocytogenes were prepared as described in Section 3.7. A volume of 10 µL of each pure EO was added to sterile filter discs with a diameter of 6 mm, and sterile water was used as control. The discs were placed on the inside center of a Petri dish lid in a sterile working hood. A control was also prepared by adding 10 µL of sterile water to the filter discs.
The inoculated agar plate was then placed to fit the lid but with the agar upwards. This created a closed Petri dish with a distance of about 1 cm between the disc and the bacteria inoculated agar surface in accordance with Goni et al. [69]. The Petri dishes were sealed with adhesive tape to prevent volatile components of the essential oils to escape.
The amount of total phenols was determined by the Folin–Ciocâlteu reagent method as described by Scalbert et al. [18]. A 10 μL volume of essential oil was dissolved in 10 mL of methanol, and 0.1 mL of methanol solution was then transferred into a volumetric flask and diluted with 0.4 mL of double distilled water and used for analysis. A Folin–Ciocâlteu reagent solution 1:10 v/v in double distilled water (1 mL) was added to the diluted methanol/oil mixture (0.5 mL), which was then mixed thoroughly and leaved for 10 minutes at room temperature. A 2 mL solution based on 15% sodium carbonate (Na2CO3·10H2O) was added; after 1 h of incubation at room temperature, the absorbance was measured at 740 nm with a UV-Vis 60 Cary spectrophotometer against a blank sample that was concomitantly prepared. The blank sample contained 0.1 mL of methanol without oil, 0.4 mL of water, 1 mL of a Folin–Ciocâlteu reagent solution, and 2 mL of a Na2CO3·10H2O solution. Gallic acid was used as the standard for the calibration curve, which was drawn using solutions of the gallic acid in methanol of different concentrations ranging between 0.01 and 1 mg/mL. Based on the measured absorbance at 740 nm, the concentration of phenolics was read (mg/mL) from the calibration line, and the total phenolics values were then expressed as mg·GAE/g·DW. Each determination was made in triplicate, and average values were reported.
The MS detection was performed on a 5975 Inert XL Agilent Technologies detector (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA), at 70 eV. Identification of chromatographic peaks was made by reference to Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) database, with a quality of recognition above 90%.
The essential oils were characterized by gas chromatography coupled with mass spectrometry detector (GC-MSD) for qualitative analysis and, with a flame ionized detector (GC-FID) (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA), quantitative analysis.
The GC analysis was performed on a 6890 Agilent Technologies chromatograph using the following parameters: a Teknokroma TR-520232 (95% dimethyl- and 5% diphenyl-polysiloxane, crosslinked; 30 m × 250 μm × 0.25 μm) capillary column, a 1 mL/min helium flow, an inlet at 175 °C, a 100:1 split ratio, and a temperature program starting at 60 °C, with a heating rate of 7 °C/min up to 200 °C and then 15 °C/min up to 300 °C, followed by isothermal heating at 300 °C for 3.33 min.
SEM examination was carried out using QUANTA 200 scanning electronic microscope (FEI Company, Hillsboro, OR, USA), with an integrated EDX system, GENESIS XM 2i EDAX (FEI Company, Hillsboro, OR, USA) with a SUTW detector and without any further treatments at different magnifications given on the image micrographs.
The film forming solutions were prepared using highly viscous chitosan from crab shells where MW = 310,000–375,000 g/mol, with a dynamic viscosity of >400 mPa·s in 1% acetic acid (20 °C). The chitosan film-forming solution was prepared by dissolving 2 g of chitosan per 100 mL of a 5% acetic acid aqueous solution. Food grade essential oils (clove, thyme, rosemary, and tea tree oils) were incorporated in a proportion of 0.75 mL/g chitosan, and Tween 80 (Sigma-Aldrich, Darmstadt, Germany) (0.125 g/g chitosan) was added as an emulsifying agent. The essential oil-added film-forming solution was homogenized with an ultrasonic processor UP50H (Hielscher—Ultrasound Technology, Teltow, Germany) using a power of 50 W at 30 kHz). The films were obtained by casting 50 mL in glass Petri dishes (153 cm2) and drying first at 25 °C in a forced-air oven for 24 h and then at 40 °C in a vacuum oven to yield a uniform thickness in all cases. Prior to analyses, the films were conditioned in desiccators for 2 days at 22 °C over a saturated solution of NaBr (58% relative humidity) [56].
Each analysis was performed in five replicates. Data were analyzed statistically with the one-way analysis of variance ANOVA test using the SPSS statistics. Significant differences between tested samples and the control were defined at p < 0.05.
The dishes were sealed with parafilm tape to prevent the volatilization of essential oils and incubated for 7 days at 25 °C. The efficacy of the treatment was evaluated after 7 days by the inhibition rate IR (%).
The antifungal activity of the tested oils was determined with the disc diffusion method. Potato dextrose agar medium was poured into 90 mm Petri dishes, and, after its solidifying, in each Petri dish, 100 μL of spore suspensions (containing 106 spores/mL) were spread onto the surface of the media. The dishes were left to facilitate the incorporation of fungi in the PDA medium for 30 min. Subsequently, filter paper discs (6 mm Ø; Whatman) were placed on the surface of the Petri dishes and impregnated with different amounts (volume from 2.5 to 60 µL) of essential oil. All determinations were performed in five replicates. Control plates (without essential oils) were inoculated using the same procedure. Each sample was evaluated by three analysts, and three averages of the five replicates were obtained. The final average is the arithmetic average of the three other averages. Samples were evaluated through estimation of the degree to which the Petri dish surface was covered by fungal mycelium and through an inhibition rate (IR) calculation.
The inhibition rate was calculated as follows:
(1)IR(%)=C−SC×100
where C is the rate of the fungal mycelium growth of the control, and S is the rate of the fungal mycelium growth of the samples.
Essential oils were screened to determine their minimum inhibitory concentration against the food spoilage microorganisms selected. The same procedure as the one described for the antifungal assay was used to determine the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC). The definition of the MIC differs between various publications [57,58,59], so it was decided that the MIC would be defined as the lowest volume of essential oil that inhibited the growth of the tested fungi with an inhibition rate higher than 80%. The MIC is expressed in different units including mg/mL [60], µg/mL [61,62], µL/L [63,64], µL/mL [65], and ppm [62,66]. In this study, the MIC of fungi was expressed as ppm.
For the determination of the antioxidant activity 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH, Sigma-Aldrich, Darmstadt, Germany), 2,2′-azino-bis(3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid) diammonium salt (ABTS, purity ≥ 98% by HPLC, Sigma-Aldrich, Darmsadt, Germany) and potassium persulfate (KPS, ACS reagent, purity ≥ 99.0%, Fluka, Buchs, Switzerland) were used. High purity solvents such as Tween-20 from Sigma-Aldrich (Buchs, Switzerland) containing lauric acid, ≥40% (balance primarily myristic, palmoyic, and stearic acids; dimethyl sulfoxide (DSMO, Sigma-Aldrich, Buchs, Switzerland), or ethanol (Sigma-Aldrich, Buchs, Switzerland) were used in the antibacterial activity test.
Four commercial essential oils used in this study were purchased from the Fares company (Orăştie, Romania): thyme (Thymus Vulgaris L.), clove (Eugenia caryophyllus—from dried floral buds of Syzygium aromaticum), rosemary (Rosmarinus officinalis L.), and tea tree (Melaleuca alternifolia aetheroleum) obtained using a distillation apparatus (according to European Pharmacopoeia 7th edition, method 8.2.12).
Polysorbate 80 or Tween® 80 (T80) is a viscous, water-soluble viscous yellow liquid, a nonionic surfactant and emulsifier often used in foods and cosmetics. It was offered by Sigma-Aldrich (Buchs, Switzerland) for research purposes.
The Folin–Ciocâlteu phenol reagent 2N was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (Buchs, Switzerland), and sodium carbonate decahydrate (Na2CO3·10H2O, M = 286.14) was from Chimopar S.A., Bucuresti, Romania. Methanol and gallic acid (97%, M = 170.12) were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (Buchs, Switzerland).
Chitosan (CS) from crab shells, with a dynamic viscosity of >400 mPa·s in 1% acetic acid (20 °C) where MW = 310,000–375,000 g/mol, was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (Buchs, Switzerland).
The results demonstrate the effectiveness of thyme EO against the food-related bacteria and fungus tested. The synergism, antagonism and additive effects, respectively, of the EOs components require further research to elucidate the mechanisms underlying their biological activity, for the purpose of accessing new natural antiseptics applicable in the pharmaceutical and food industry.
The antimicrobial activity of EOs depends on their chemical constituents. Apparently, the antimicrobial activity of the EO analyzed is related to the presence of phenolic compounds (thymol) and terpene hydrocarbons (γ-terpinene), respectively [4,7,18]. p-Cymene, the third major element according to percentage, does not show antibacterial efficacy when used alone [7], synergistic effects being however attributed to it in relation to thymol and γ-terpinene, respectively [19,20], which might represent another cause of the antimicrobial activity recorded. On the other hand, a number of studies have shown that EOS exhibit stronger antimicrobial activity than that of their major constituents or their mixtures, respectively [21,22], which suggests synergistic effects of the minor components, but also the importance of all components in relation to the biological activity of EOs.
The isolation yield was 1.25% (v/w), based on dry plant material and confirmed that the plant analyzed meets the requirements of pharmaceutical quality for thyme as EO source [3]. The chemical composition determined by GC/ MS is presented in Table 1. Fifteen components representing 99.91% of the total detected constituents were identified. The major components were p-cymene (8.41%), γ-terpinene (30.90%) and thymol (47.59%), which suggests that the EO analyzed belongs to the thymol chemotype in agreement with those previously reported in Romania [2]. The other components were present in a total amount of less than 13.01%. The chemical composition of the EO analyzed by us is very different from that previously reported in Morocco and Spain for the same species of thyme [11,12]. Similar studies in Poland, Iran, Spain and Italy, respectively, reported as major compounds in the T. vulgaris EO p-cymene, γ-terpinene and thymol [4,13-15]. These differences can be attributed to a large extent to the different chemotypes mentioned above [4,5,13].
The inhibitions are expressed in mm and include the diameter of the paper disc (6 mm). Data distributions were expressed as mean values and standard deviations (SD) (n = 9). Ciprofloxacine and cephalexine (for bacterial strains) and fluconazole (for fungi), respectively, were used as positive controls.
The antimicrobial activity of thyme oil against 7 common food-related bacteria and fungus tested is presented in Table 2. The null hypothesis that the inhibition zone is equal to the disc diameter (6 mm) was rejected for each microorganism at every amount of essential oil with a high significance level (p = 0.00). The main finding of the ANOVA analysis is a strong interaction effect between the type of microorganism and the amount of essential oil (p = 0.00). The highly significant interaction effect adds difficulty in drawing general conclusions on the main effects, even if the two factors are also highly significant (p = 0.00). For example, K. pneumoniae has the highest inhibition zone overall but for the amount of 20 [μL], where E. coli and S. typhimurium have higher values. In order to compare more thoroughly the effect of T. vulgaris on each microorganism (Fig. 1), the results of multiple comparisons, at each oil amount, has to be considered. Tukey’s HSD test reveals that the only microorganisms with non-significant differences in the antimicrobial effect are S. typhimurium and E. coli at all oil amounts, and S. typhimurium, E. coli and C. albicans at 10 [μL]. The observed p-value for the pairwise differences in the above-mentioned cases does not pass acceptable significance levels, being larger than 0.4. All the other pairwise differences are highly significant (p = 0.00).
The inhibition of the growth of E. coli, K. pneumoniae, S. aureus, P. aeruginosa and E. faecalis was previously reported [4,7,9] along with the efficacy against C. albicans [9,16,17] and S. typhimurium [4,9], respectively. In contrast, some studies report the inefficiency of thyme EO against E. coli [16,17], S. aureus [16] and K. pneumoniae [16].
The aim of this study is to determine the chemical composition together with the antimicrobial properties of the EO of T. vulgaris cultivated in Romania, in order to identify new sources of natural antiseptics with applications in the pharmaceutical and food industry.
The genus Thymus, member of the Lamiaceae family, contains about 400 species of perennial aromatic, evergreen or semi-evergreen herbaceous plants with many subspecies, varieties, subvarieties and forms [1]. In Romania, the Thymus genus contains one species cultivated as aromatic plant (Thymus vulgaris) and other 18 wild species [2]. T. vulgaris (thyme), locally known as “cimbru”, is widely used in the Romanian folk medicine for its expectorant, antitussive, antibroncholitic, antispasmodic, anthelmintic, carminative and diuretic properties.
Various studies have aimed to investigate the chemical composition and biological properties of the T. vulgaris essential oil (EO). According to European Pharmacopoeia 5.0 (Ph. Eur. 5.0) [3], the minimum content of EO in T. vulgaris is 12 mL/kg, but the chemical composition shows variations, six chemotypes being mainly reported, namely geraniol, linalool, gamma-terpineol, carvacrol, thymol and trans-thujan-4-ol/terpinen-4-ol [4,5]. Both the isolation yield and the chemical composition of the EOs are dependent on a number of factors, such as the environment, growth region and cultivation practices [6]. In addition to the flavoring properties determined by the constitutive active ingredients, the thyme EO exhibits significant antimicrobial activity [4,7-9] as well as strong antioxidant properties [2,8].
Gas chromatography-mass spectrometry. Samples were analyzed by gas chromatography using a HP6890 instrument coupled with a HP 5973 mass spectrometer. The gas chromatograph is equipped with a split-splitless injector and a Factor FourTM VF-35ms 5% fenil-methylpolysiloxane, 30 m, 0.25 mm, 0.25 μm film thickness capillary column. Gas chromatography conditions include a temperature range of 50 to 250°C at 40°C/min, with a solvent delay of 5 min. The injector was maintained at a temperature of 250°C. The inert gas was helium at a flow of 1.0 mL/min, and the injected volume in the splitless mode was 1 μL. The MS conditions were the following: ionization energy, 70 eV; quadrupole temperature, 100°C; scanning velocity, 1.6 scan/s; weight range, 40-500 amu.
Raw material. Thyme was harvested during the flowering season (July 2012) from the area around the Broşteni commune – Mehedinţi County, Romania. The plant material was dried in well-ventilated areas, sheltered from direct sunlight and then stored in double-layered paper bags at temperatures of 3-5°C until processing. A voucher specimen (V.FPT-451) was deposited in the Herbarium of the Faculty of Pharmacy, “Victor Babeș” University of Medicine and Pharmacy, Timișoara, Romania.
Determination of antimicrobial activity. Thyme EO was tested on 7 common food-related bacteria and fungus: Staphylococcus aureus (ATCC 25923), Pseudomonas aeruginosa (ATCC 27853), Salmonella typhimurium (ATCC 14028), Escherichia coli (ATCC 25922), Klebsiella pneumoniae (ATCC 13882), Enterococcus faecalis (ATCC 29212) and Candida albicans (ATCC 10231), using the disk diffusion method as previously described [10]. Briefly, a suspension of the tested microorganism (10^6 cells/mL-1) was spread on the solid media plates (Mueller-Hinton agar for bacteria and Sabouraud cloramphenicol agar for fungi). The paper discs (Whatman No 1 filter paper - 6 mm diameter) were impregnated with 5, 10, 15 and 20µL EO and placed on the inoculated agar. The plates inoculated with bacterial strains were incubated for 24 h at 37°C and 48 h at 30°C for fungi, respectively. As positive controls, ciprofloxacin (30 µg/disk) and cephalexin (10 µg/disk) were used for bacterial strains and fluconazole (10 µg/disk) for fungi. After incubation, the diameter of the zone of inhibition was measured in millimeters. Each test was performed in triplicate on at least three separate experiments.
Isolation of essential oils. The EO was obtained by hydrodistillation, according to Ph. Eur. 5.0 [3], by using a modified Clevenger apparatus (with the EO collection area cooled to prevent the emergence of artifacts). The EO was dried on anhydrous sodium sulfate (Sigma-Aldrich Chemie GmbH) and stored in a tightly sealed brown glass bottle at 0-4°C for testing.
Statistical analysis. The statistical analysis was performed by using SPSS Version 21 (IBM Corp., NY). The mean inhibition zone for each group of nine observations was compared with the value of the disc diameter (6 mm) using the t-test. The GLM procedure was used to conduct a two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) on the inhibition zones. The type of microorganism and amount of essential oil were used as factors in the full factorial model. Post-hoc tests for each amount of essential oil were conducted by using Tukey’s HSD method, in order to compare the effect on different types of microorganisms.
The percent composition of the volatile compounds was calculated. The qualitative analysis was based on the percent area of each peak of the sample compounds. The mass spectrum of each compound was compared with the mass spectrum from the NIST 98 spectrum library (USA National Institute of Science and Technology software).